Register of the Donald Marquand Dozer Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1893-1980
  - United States - Bicentennial celebration, 1976
    - Massachusetts. Revolutionary War Bicentennial Commission
      - Newsletters, 1966-1971 (Folder 2)
  - United States - Foreign relations
    - General
      - General, Notes, clippings, form letters, speech transcripts (John Foster Dulles, Walter H. Judd, Styles Bridges, David K. Bruce and John Rarick), draft resolution by John F. Dulles, letter with speech transcript from John W. Bricker, pamphlets, flyer, printed article and book excerpt, printed and mimeographed reports by the General Electric TEMPO Project, The Developing Power Centers of the World: 1970-1975, and A World in Transition, 1941-1977. (Folder 3-7)
      - Jenner, William E. Speech transcripts and press releases, 1951-1958 (Folder 8-10)
    - Conference materials, 1955-1976 (Folder 11)
  - United States - Government
    - General, Reprint, pamphlet, memorandum, newsletter, mimeographed report on the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and a speech transcript (William E. Jenner), 1952-1977. (Box 131, Folder 1)
    - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations. Printed reports, 1974-1975 (Folder 2-3)
    - Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government. Flyers, printed pamphlets, speech transcript (John M. Harlan), 1959-1964 (Folder 4)
  - United States - Law. Letters, newsletters, pamphlets, speech transcripts (William E. Jenner), mimeographed and printed reports and pamphlets, 1942-1978 (Folder 5-7)
  - United States - Politics
    - Organizations
      - General
        - General
          - Correspondence, Includes letters neither to nor from Dr. Dozer, with many enclosures, 1960-1979. (Folder 8-9)
          - Non-printed material. Flyers, speech transcript, form letters, radio broadcast transcripts ("Clarion Call"), resolutions, mimeographed reports, verses, miscellany
            - 1958 (Folder 10)
            - 1959-1977 (Box 132, Folder 1-3)
          - Printed material, Clippings, excerpts and articles, speech transcript, pamphlet, flyers, 1955-1977. (Folder 4-6)
        - Newsletters
          - General, 1955-1979 (Folder 7-9)
          - America's Future, Includes pamphlet and form letter, 1973-1979. (Folder 10-11)
          - Armed Forces Roll Call Newsletter, 1963-1965 (Folder 12)
          - New Right Report, 1978-1979 (Folder 13)
          - U.S.A., 1978-1979 (Box 133, Folder 1)
          - World Research INK, 1978-1979 (Folder 2)
      - Accuracy in Media, Inc. Newsletter (AIM Report) and letters, 1972-1975. (Folder 3)
      - American Coalition of Patriotic Societies. Resolutions, newsletter, constitution, memoranda, meeting agenda, 1961-1974 (Folder 4)
      - American Conservative Union
        - General, Pamphlets, flyers, clippings and miscellany, 1966-1971. (Folder 5)
        - Memoranda and correspondence, 1965-1976 (Folder 6)
        - Newsletters, 1965-1969 (Folder 7)
        - Press releases, 1965-1969 (Folder 8)
        - Reports and statements, 1965-1966 (Folder 9)
      - Americanism Educational League (William E. Fort, Jr.). Flyer, speech transcript, mimeographed report, pamphlets, correspondence, newsletters and miscellany, 1959-1974 (Folder 10)
      - Center for Constructive Alternatives (Rousas J. Rushdoony). Newsletter (Imprimis), printed article, pamphlet and flyer, 1965-1972. (Folder 11)
      - Committee to Restore the Constitution (T. David Horton). Letters, pamphlets, newsletter, miscellany, speech and hearing transcripts, 1963-1977 (Folder 12-13)
      - Daughters of the American Revolution. Speech transcripts, letter, printed article, flyer, resolutions, 1957-1967 (Folder 14)
      - Defenders of the American Constitution, Inc. (Includes Voters for Enforcing the Constitution)
        - General. Newsletters, flyers, statements and position papers, clippings, 1961-1965 (Box 134, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence, Includes letters to Governors George C. Wallace, Nelson Rockefeller, J. Millard Tawes and Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., 1935-1971. (Folder 2-3)
      - Freedom School (Rampart College). Newsletters, pamphlets and letters, 1965-1972 (Folder 4)
      - National Right to Work Legal Defense Foundation, Inc. Newsletter (National Right to Work Committee Newsletter), letters and form letters, 1976-1979 (Folder 5)
      - Sons of the American Revolution. Letters, 1962-1975 (Folder 6)
      - Young Americans for Freedom (Includes Students for Victory in Vietnam)
        - General, Form letter, newsletters, conference materials, reports, notes, agenda and minutes, flyers, poster and serial issues, 1966-1973. (Folder 7-9)
        - Correspondence, 1964-1977 (Folder 10)
    - Parties. Republican
      - General. Primarily correspondence (including a holograph draft of a letter to Caspar W. Weinberger); also includes speech transcripts (Sens. Carl T. Curtis and William E. Jenner) and clippings, 1953-1977 (Folder 11-12)
      - National
        - General, Mimeographed report, press release, form letters, chart, platform positions, clippings and correspondence, including the Republican National Committee and a letter from Ben E. Tate, acting for Sen. Robert A. Taft, 1952-1976. (Folder 13)
        - Nixon, Richard M. Clippings, press release, correspondence and campaign materials, 1968-1971 (Folder 14)
        - Reagan, Ronald
          - General. Form letters, flyer, pamphlet, gubernatorial report, letter, 1966-1978 (Box 135, Folder 1)
          - Newsletter (Citizens for the Republic), 1978-1979 (Folder 2)
      - State. Campaign materials, newsletters, pamphlets, by-laws, certificate, letters, mimeographed report, flyers, dates, 1962-1971 (Folder 3)
      - Local (Santa Barbara Republican Central Committee)
        - General. Clippings, certificates, resolutions, agenda and minutes, by-laws, directories, financial statements, 1962-1976 (Folder 4)
        - Correspondence, 1962-1973 (Folder 5)
  - Vietnam. Clippings, newsletter, mimeographed report, and letters from Jay Goodan, a friend of the Dozer family stationed in Vietnam, 1954-circa 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Watergate. Letter from the Public Information Office, Watergate Special Prosecution force to William Collier, 1976 (Folder 7)
  - Women. "Women and the Law," Fifth Annual Southern California Conference, UCLA, Letters, proposal and a mimeographed report, 1976, 1976 october 30-31. (Folder 8)
  - World War II. Predominantly revisionist history relating to Pearl Harbor. Printed articles, speech transcripts (Arthur Marder, Curtis Dall), letters (Harry E. Barnes, Husband E. Kimmel, Curtis B. Dall), questionnaire, pamphlet, notes, letter to the editor and mimeographed report by Harry E. Barnes, "Pearl Harbor Comes of Age in a Thermonuclear Era," and an anonymous mimeographed report, "The Mystery of the Merle-Smith Message,", 1952-1978 (Folder 9-12)
  - Zimbabwe (Rhodesia). Pamphlets, form letters and newsletters (American Southern Africa Council), press release, letters, questionnaire, clippings, speech transcripts (John R. Rarick, John M. Ashbrook), SEE ALSO: Africa/American-African Affairs Association, 1965-1972. (Folder 13-14)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS FILE-B, 1948-1979
  Drafts, manuscript copies, printed copies, reports, press releases speech transcripts, notes and source materials, correspondence and other miscellany. These writings relate specifically to the World War II publication controversy and Donald M. Dozer's personal experiences in the State Department. Arranged chronologically.
  - "Our Trojan Horse in Washington," Fragmentary typescript draft, correspondence, speech transcript (John Foster Dulles) and mimeographed reports by H.M. Somers, "Bureaucracy and the Change of Administration," Howard White, "The Problem of Loyalty in American Political Thought," Eleanor Bontecou, "President Eisenhower's Personnel Security Program," and L.L. Friedland, "The Career System Revisited,", 1953 october 1953-1954 (Box 136, Folder 1)
  - Letter to the Editor. Typescript, 1955 december (Folder 2)
  - "What the State Department Won't Tell You," Typescript, circa 1956.
    - General
      - Correspondence, Includes Robert Welch, George Morgenstern and Julius Epstein, 1954-1978. (Folder 3)
      - Source material, Flyers, newsletters, letter and miscellany, 1953-1972. (Folder 4)
    - Preface (Folder 5)
    - 1. The Untold Story (Folder 6)
    - 2. A New Republican President (Folder 7)
    - 3. A New State Department Program (Folder 8)
    - 4. A Record of Non-performance (Folder 9)
    - 5. Scapegoats and Reprisals (Folder 10)
  - "Let the People Know," Typescript and correspondence (with reviews), 1956. 1955-1956 (Folder 11)
  - "History Takes a Holiday," Represents a synthesis of earlier unpublished material relating to liberalism as a political philosophy (primarily in America) as well as Dr. Dozer's State Department experiences ("What the State Department Won't Tell You"). Several chapters from this manuscript were eventually published as individual essays., 1961.
    - General
      - Correspondence (with reviews), Includes Henry Regnery, 1954-1967. (Folder 12-14)
      - Source material
        - Non-printed material, Letters, newsletters, mimeographed and typescript reports, press releases and speech transcripts (including Allen W. Dulles, John Foster Dulles, Clare Boothe Luce), 1951-1966. (Folder 15-16)
        - Printed material, Serial issues, pamphlets, newsletters, printed articles, clippings, 1948-1972. (Box 137, Folder 1-7)
    - Table of Contents and Preface (Folder 8)
    - 1. The European Dynasts (Folder 9)
    - 2. Accent on America (Folder 10)
    - 3. The Power and the Glory (Folder 11)
    - 4. Totalitarian Diplomacy (Folder 12)
    - 5. Public Censors (Folder 13)
    - 6. Liberalism--Old and New (Folder 14)
    - 7. The Dilemma of Freedom (Folder 15)
    - 8. History as Force (SEE ALSO: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/ /"History As Force"), 1965 november (Folder 16)
    - 9. A Responsive Government (Folder 17)
    - 10. The Transfer of Power (Box 138, Folder 1)
    - 11. The Policy of the Free Hand (Folder 2)
    - 12. The Dragon's Teeth (Folder 3)
    - 13. The Heavenly City (Folder 4)
    - 14. East River Citadel (Folder 5)
    - 15. Epilogue (Folder 6)
    - Bibliography (Folder 7)
  - Foreign Relations of the United States, Diplomatic Papers: The Conferences at Cairo and Tehran, 1943, Annotated copy, letters and clipping, 1961. (Folder 8)
  - "Eyes Only Diplomacy," Holograph draft and letters, 1972. (Folder 9)
  - "Watergate Prelude,", circa 1976
    - General
      - General, Clippings and press releases, 1951-1979. (Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Folder 11)
    - 1. The President as War Maker
      - Draft A (earlier, longer version, planned for publication as separate article) (Folder 12)
      - Draft B (first chapter of manuscript expanded from above) (Folder 13)
    - 2. Commander-in-Chief (Box 139, Folder 1)
    - 3. A New Republican President. Chapters 3-6 are from the earlier manuscript "What the State Department Won't Tell You" (Folder 2)
    - 4. A New State Department Program (Folder 3)
    - 5. A Record of Non-Performance (Folder 4)
    - 6. Scapegoats and Reprisals (Folder 5)
    - 8. The President's Tenure of Office. Originally developed as an article, this material became a chapter in this manuscript.
      - General. Correspondence, Includes brief correspondence with Archibald Cox; also includes correspondence about a related (?) manuscript, "A Four-Year Term for Congressman", 1951-1974. (Folder 6)
      - Text
        - Draft A (earlier version, includes review) (Folder 7)
        - Draft B (final version?) (Folder 8)
- U.S. GOVERNMENT SERVICE FILE-B, 1951-1977.
  Reports, memoranda, personnel materials, correspondence, clippings, notes, speech and hearing transcripts, press releases, newsletters, pamphlets, flyers, resolutions, serial issues, and other miscellany. These materials relate specifically to the World War II publication controversy and Donald M. Dozer's personal experiences in the State Department. Arranged by subject (individual names).
  - General
    - General (Box 139, Folder 9-10)
      - General, Speech transcripts, newsletters, pamphlets, hearing transcripts, reports, resolutions, serial issue, miscellany, 1952-1972.
      - Clippings
        - General. Yalta transcripts, (Published, 1955. March 17 and december 30) (Folder 11)
        - 1952 november-1955 March 16 (Folder 12)
        - 1955 March 17-31 (Folder 13)
        - 1955 April-1968 september 11 (Folder 14)
    - Barron, Bryton, (Mr. Barron was a colleague of Dr. Dozer's, and was pressured out of the State Department about the same time), 1956-1972.
      - General, Typed transcript of Senate testimony, flyers, book promotional material, press releases, newsletter, and a printed article entitled, "Otto Otepka and the State Department", 1956-1964. (Box 140, Folder 1)
      - Clippings, 1956-1972 (Folder 2)
      - Correspondence. SEE: Dozer,Donald/ Correspondence/Barron, Bryton
  - Dozer, Donald M.
    - Clippings
      - 1955 october (Folder 3-4)
      - 1955 november-december (Folder 5)
      - 1956 (Folder 6-7)
      - 1957-1958 (Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1976
      - General. Arranged alphabetically (Folder 9-12)
      - Agnew, Spiro, 1970 (Folder 13)
      - Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1957-1968 (Folder 14)
      - Barron, Bryton, 1956-1976 (Box 141, Folder 1-2)
      - Bender, George H. (Senator), 1955 (Folder 3)
      - Bow, Frank T. (M.C.), 1957-1960 (Folder 4)
      - Bricker, John W. (Senator), Includes a letter from Senator Bricker to Secretary Dulles, 1953-1976. (Folder 5)
      - Bridges, Styles (Senator), 1955-1960 (Folder 6)
      - Briggs, Ellis O., 1955-1956 (Folder 7)
      - Buckley, William F., Jr., 1970 (Folder 8)
      - Butler, John Marshall (Senator), 1953-1954 (Folder 9)
      - Chicago Tribune (George Morgenstern and Walter Trohan), 1954-1960 (Folder 10)
      - Daniels, Paul Clement, 1955-1956 (Folder 11)
      - Doty, Wayne L., 1956-1957 (Folder 12)
      - Dunn, Waldo H., 1951-1961 (Folder 13)
      - Dulles, John Foster, 1955 (Folder 14)
      - Epstein, Julius, Includes material relating to Epstein's attempts to secure government information, 1955-1974. (Folder 15)
      - Fellers, Bonner (Brig. Gen.), 1958 (Folder 16)
      - Fino, Paul A. (M.C.), 1959 (Folder 17)
      - Foundation for Economic Education, 1955 (Folder 18)
      - Fuller, Vincent J., 1958 (Folder 19)
      - Henderson, John E. (M.C.), 1957 (Folder 20)
      - Hoover, Herbert, 1961 (Folder 21)
      - Hussey, Roland, 1955 (Folder 22)
      - Kent, Frederick H., 1957 (Folder 23)
      - Knowland, William F. (Senator), 1956 (Folder 24)
      - Kohlberg, Alfred, 1957 (Folder 25)
      - Lowry, Howard Foster, 1957 (Folder 26)
      - McCardle, Carl, undated (Folder 27)
      - Moss, John E. (M.C.), Hearing transcripts and cover letter, 1957. (Folder 28)
      - Neumann, William L., 1953-1957 (Folder 29)
      - New Bedford Standard Times (Charles Lewin), 1954-1962 (Folder 30)
      - Reid, John Gilbert, Includes letters written by Reid to various U.S. Senators, 1953-1977. (Folder 31)
      - Republican National Committee, 1955-1956 (Folder 32)
      - Robb, Roger, 1960-1972 (Folder 33)
      - Roosevelt, Archibald, 1957 (Folder 34)
      - Smoot, Dan, 1957-1958 (Folder 35)
      - SPX Research Associates (Col. Tom R. Hutton), 1956 (Folder 36)
      - Wayne, John, 1964 (Folder 37)
      - Woodward, Robert F., 1955-1961 (Folder 38)
    - Memoranda, Includes some routine divisional material, 1953-1956 january (Box 142, Folder 1-3)
    - Monthly reports (submitted by Dr. Dozer), 1953 June-1955 december (Folder 4)
    - Notes
      - Relating to the controversy over the publication program. Predominantly notes and fragments for book (SEE: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS FILE-B/ /"What the State Department Won't Tell You"), circa 1956
        - Dated, 1953-1958 (Folder 5)
        - Undated (Folder 6-9)
      - Relating to the actual subject material
        - General (Folder 10)
        - White, Harry Dexter. Summary and notes on his papers at Princeton University (Folder 11)
    - Personnel material. Correspondence relating to Dr. Dozer's dismissal, 1955-1956 (Box 143, Folder 1-2)
    - Statements, Typescripts and holographs, more substantial notes, letters and other materials by Dr. Dozer, relating to his experience. Includes text for press conference, 1954-1957. (Folder 3-4)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  Notes relating to anti-imperialist sentiment in the United States and miscellany, primarily oversize printed material.
  - Index cards. Notes relating to anti-imperialist sentiment in the United States. SEE ALSO: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS FILE/ /"American Opposition to Territorial Expansion, ", circa 1946 1865-1895 (Box 144-147)
  - Miscellanea, Primarily oversize printed materials relating to the West Coast general strike, the United States Bicentennial celebration, United States foreign relations and Latin America, 1934-1979. (Box 148)
- PHONORECORDS
  - 1 record entitled, "Todo por la Patria," of a speech by General Omar Torrijos Herrera, 1971 october 11 (Record-cabinet cabinet)
- PHONOTAPES
  - 1 phonotape recording of Panama Canal Zone Citizens Council meeting, 1975 august 21 (Tape-cabinet cabinet)
- PHONOTAPE CASSETTES
  - The Panama Canal: America's Next Vietnam, 1.0 sound cassette (Cassette-cabinet cabinet)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 70011_a_0010337
    Sound recording of a television debate.
  - Discussion on Latin American economic development, 1.0 sound cassette (Cassette-cabinet cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 70011_a_0010341
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  108 prints, 6 postcards, 9 negatives in 8 envelopes.
  - 3 prints of Donald M. Dozer in Latin America; 3 prints of Lewis A. Tambs in Latin America; 6 old color postcards of Latin America, 1963 (Envelope A)
  - 48 prints (28 duplicates) and 8 negatives prepared for Latin America: An Interpretive History. Primarily Argentina, 1962 (Envelope B-C)
  - 18 prints (4 duplicates) of an awards ceremony and a ship involved in the United States Bicentennial celebration, 1976 (Envelope D-E)
  - 7 miscellaneous prints and 1 negative, including Erving Winslow, and Reps. Daniel Flood and Charles Teague (tentative identification) undated, and 2 group prints 1950-1957 (Envelope F)
  - 25 prints of the Panama Canal, 1895-1972 (Envelope G)
  - 2 oversize prints of the Panama Canal, circa 1960 (Envelope mH)
- VIDEOCASSETTES
  - 1 videocassette entitled, "Fifty Miles of Trouble: The Panama Canal,", 1978 february 15 (Tape-cabinet cabinet)
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1966
  - 2018 release of declassified records, 1966 (Reading room workstation)